The sutas often talk about um sense
objects. So what is how would you explain to say
So what is how would you explain to say
somebody
that wants to practice
what is a sense objects? What are sense
objects? How do you find them in your
experience? How do you define them
rightly?
Well, first of all, you have to be
restrained in your actions. Um, because
through your actions,
you put yourself in a position where
you're already immersed in sense objects
and therefore you're not able to even
see them as arisen things that you could
get immersed in. Um so
in order to be able to see what a sense
object is, you basically have to
look at what are the ways in which
regardless of what views you have about
the sense objects, you would already be
uh involved with them. And so that's
sensuality, not keeping the precepts,
these kinds of actions, like even though
you might then philosophize about what
sense objects are, you're already
completely um tunnel visioned into them
simply by living in that way. So then if
that's established, you're mostly
withdrawn from those actions. Then sense
objects would kind of be the
it's you they're not things that you can
observe or get focused on in the same
way as you know the the or the the wrong
way that people will go about it is
trying to focus on their sensations
usually. But um and and this idea that
it's uh zoning in on them and and
zooming in on them. But really you have
to see sense objects includes the mind
as well. Mental objects those are the
ones that most people are often not
aware of and not clear about that. These
are um
options of
you could almost call them like options
of exploration, options of um
going down and
exploring the particulars as the sutas
describe. And the task is not to then
find a particular definition of what
sense objects are, but learn how to not
get absorbed in those particulars as
such. See them as options that you could
get absorbed in, but you choose not to.
>> So, but I mean what one could argue that
sight, sounds, smell, taste, touches is
something you can zoom in on.
>> Yeah, you can. But that's the thing. If
you do, you lose perspective of
Not because the thing is you don't want
to have perspective over sense objects.
You want to have perspective over the
dimension of the senses.
>> Right. But the question is are those the
sense objects?
>> What do you mean?
>> Sight, smell, taste, touches.
>> Yeah. But um like those are sense
objects, but
that's not where the problem that's not
where your development should be. It's
it shouldn't be about examining them or
zooming on them further. You want to see
the domain of the eye, the domain of the
ear, the domain of the
>> What is that? That's that's too
abstract. That's too abstract for say
>> anybody that's not familiar with
philosophy. It's like so I want to
practice. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> The sutas talk about sense objects.
Um you said I shouldn't be zooming in on
them, >> shouldn't be um how do you say lose
>> shouldn't be um how do you say lose
perspective and so on.
Um and I should be seeing the domain
instead. What is that? What is uh how do
I make sense of that?
>> Well, the domain is like
>> practically give me an example
>> where the where you find the pressure to
go to to examine further to look further
>> smell further
>> such as um sensuality in general,
pleasant sense objects.
>> Mhm. things that you're not just you
shouldn't just examine random neutral
sense objects in the world. You will
understand this principle if you go
where the pressure is things that are
emotionally charged in one way or
another that you can't just be
indifferent towards. And is the right so
you're saying that um one should look at
the pressure
pressure
>> that one feels towards sight sounds
smell taste touches
>> rather than examining sight sounds smell
taste touches is that correctly is that
correctly understood?
>> Yeah. So find the pressure first
and then through that you will get to
see that um principle of descending onto
the particulars that the sut describe.
>> But what if what if there's no pressure?
What if I can't see any pressure?
Well, if that's truly the case, then
either you're an arhan or there's
something that you're overlooking,
something that you're still because you
have you cannot be neutral. You cannot
be in like a neutral
um completely uninvolved uh situation.
You have to be um
over attending something.
Unless your mind is fully developed, you
will be over attending or not seeing,
not having perspective in regard to some
sense object. Even if it's neutral,
ambiguous, unclear
unclear
>> in regard to sense objects, not having
perspective. >> Yeah. So what you mean?
>> Yeah. So what you mean?
>> Because the mental.
>> So if I feel no pressure, I mean
like somebody might legitimately say,
well, I'm not pressured to look at
anything. So what do I do then? Well,
but are you are you is there something
that you are
>> like I feel neutally. There's no
pressure. There's no craving. There's no
there's no lust. There's no aversion. I
feel neutally. What where's the
pressure? What do I look for?
>> Well, but the thing is
>> according to you, [clears throat]
pressure is always there.
>> Yeah,
>> that's what you said. So, where is it?
>> Well, it's pressure is always there, but
it's not going to be always in a way
that you expect to find it.
>> So, how do they find it? you can in in
that state of let's say supposedly not
being pressured. Um, you might not be
pressured towards the specific things
that you were pressured before, but can
you truly say that if you just kind of
take your hands off the situation, so to
speak, that the mind won't be drifting
into something on its own,
>> such as boredom or fantasizing things
about the past or planning about the
future or even just a state of dullness,
which kind of carries its own momentum.
You didn't you didn't ask for it. It
just comes comes like that on its own.
>> So then if that's if if that's still
there that means well that's that that
is another experience another object I
guess you could say which you would also
have to maintain perspective in regard
to that the those other directions that
you would be falling down into
when there's no no pressure. Um you
don't want to think as if oh there's
nothing here.
>> So in other words just wait a bit and
see cuz the pressure will come up.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Or if some if seemingly there is
no pressure it's not well it's either
because as you said you had already hunt
or it's because you're simply not
discerning it at the time.
>> Yeah. So it will it will it will be
clear that in that state even when you
thought there wasn't pressure there was
some at least
>> like a subtler pressure than what you're
used to
>> that doesn't might not fit the
definition of like the coarse sensuality
that you were expecting
>> but clearly the mind would be kind of
tugging >> it's not neutral
>> it's not neutral
>> exactly
>> so so then would you say that so sense
object sense object is something you can
tend to focus fus on uh concentrate look
at directly but as as you said that's
not the point
>> the point is to look at the pressure
that's making you do it.
>> Yeah. Because in the sutras it's not
just um understanding the sense objects
is understanding the sense bases
>> and the sense bases are completely
obscured to the extent that you descend
into the objects. But if I just, you
know, study
the the sights,
>> wouldn't that reveal me the nature of
vision, nature of the eye?
>> Well, no, because it's the eye that you
would be using to study the sites. So,
>> you it's like like a camera recording
itself kind of thing. You can't possibly
arrive at it through
examining the objects that come on
account of it. But what if I really
really study the sites like to the to
the kind of microscopic degree
>> in between the moments like like like
really to the greatest detail?
>> Wouldn't that show me
>> the eye as the as described the eye is
like or all of the six senses they're
like these animals that are pulling you
in separate directions. So it's not this
kind of um technical sort of mechanism
that you discover. It's that the the eye
is on the level of that pressure that
you feel. It's it's more a direction of
that um being pulled rather than again
some mechanism that you understand. So,
so what you're saying is that regardless
of
how particular things I might be seeing
or how general sites the eye might be
looking at,
nowhere in that domain, nowhere in that
field of like the atomic particles
>> or you know staring at the gigantic
mountains. >> Nowhere in that field is I to be found.
>> Nowhere in that field is I to be found.
Doesn't matter how slowly, how
precisely, as I said, how meticulously, how
as I said, how meticulously, how
microscopically you're looking. Simply I
cannot be anywhere there.
>> Yeah. And would I describe it as these
empty uh villages or empty kind of like
>> which one?
>> The sense spaces.
>> Uhhuh.
>> That that are attacked by bandits. So
then >> bandits being
>> bandits being
>> bandits being the sense objects.
>> Uhhuh.
>> So
>> raiding.
>> Yeah. Being raided by the entity. So if
you are examining sense object, doesn't
matter how complex or special they are,
you're examining the bandits. You're not
examining the empty village.
>> Mhm.
>> So that empty village can only become
apparent as such precisely when you stop
being concerned and engaged with the
some extent of bandits that will
inevitably be there.
>> Microscopic bandits.
>> Yeah.
the So, so then the sight, sounds,
smell, taste, touches are attacking the
fields. >> They're not, it's not that the fields
>> They're not, it's not that the fields
are there. Well, hold on. Is that what
you're saying? I don't know.
>> Yeah.
>> So, it's not that the fields are there
seeing side, sounds, smell, taste,
touches. >> Fields are there known because they're
>> Fields are there known because they're
being attacked.
>> Exactly. Yeah.
>> So, you can't
>> So, can you explain that? So you can't
uh try to abstract the eye as a as an
independent thing that you find like
first purely by itself.
>> Why not? I mean you can surely think it.
>> Yes. But
>> what's the problem with that?
>> But the eye has to be found as an
implication when sense objects are there
but they're not being absorbed and
focused on.
>> But what is this eye that I'm thinking
of? >> Well, that's another mental image.
>> Well, that's another mental image.
And uh what's the problem with that?
>> Well, it's not a
>> I can focus and not not forget about it
and concentrate on it and think about it
frequently. >> But that's the thing. It's that would if
>> But that's the thing. It's that would if
it's divorced from the sites.
>> If it's divorced from what's felt in
regard to the sites, if it's divorced
from that pressure.
>> Mhm.
>> Then that's not the actual eye that
because of which you suffer because that
you have all these assumptions in regard
to. So it's the eye that
has some kind of pressured relationship
towards the sights. That's the one that
you want to see, not just an idea of it.
So if what you're saying is if you don't
see the or if it becomes devoid from a
pressure it ceases to be that
>> eye that field that
>> phenomenon
>> because it's a it again it's if if
there's not that pull then it's not that
animal of the eye
>> that the Buddha described is just some
idea that then
>> as much as you might develop it is
disconnected from the problem of
suffering. >> Mhm. So say I make the effort now and
>> Mhm. So say I make the effort now and
catch myself when I start falling into
abstractions or um focusing and
concentrations on the sense objects
thinking that will reveal me the true
nature of the eye or the fields or the
village the empty village.
>> So how do I train rightly then fully to
completely fully surmount
that whole um duality of sense objects
and um
>> sense fields.
>> Right. Well, starts with the same thing
that I described in the beginning. You
have to be you have to have ceased um
specific actions toward those sense
objects that automatically have you
taking for granted that pressure and not
seeing it by just acting out of it. Then
on the basis of that you have to keep an
eye throughout your day on that pressure
that will be there to some extent. You
have to because as soon as you
start ignoring it and overlooking it,
you're automatically
taking it up. It's not a separate uh
movement. You're automatically
um failing to see that village being
attacked by bandits.
>> How do how do I avoid falling into
ignoring it and overlooking it?
>> Well, it's
>> do I need to do I need to concentrate on
it the whole day?
>> That's the thing. It's it's
even if you were to go and concentrate,
it wouldn't change anything about the
fact where of where it already is. I
risen on its own. So, you have to
>> But concentrating can help me stay in
touch with it. No.
>> Well, but that's the thing. Anything
you're concentrating into
>> Mhm.
>> is already like it's almost like you had
to stay at the beginning of this path to
see the crossroads, so to speak. Mhm.
>> And anything that you concentrate on,
you're just going down one of those
crossroads. >> So you have
>> So you have
>> You mean like if I start concentrating,
I lose
contact with that pressure?
>> Yeah.
>> Because of which I would be
concentrating. >> The pressure is still there, but your
>> The pressure is still there, but your
emphasis and your your kind of weight of
your attention is now directed in such a
way that you won't be able to see it.
>> Okay. So how do I then not lose the
sight of it without needing to
concentrate on it? Well, you just have
to ask yourself because again, well,
first of all,
>> what if it's just something comes up and
naturally distracts me? Does that mean I
lost the sight?
>> No, because even then you can be aware
of how you're being pressured in regard
to that new thing that arose.
You you don't have to focus on that. You
don't have to um kind of uh overly
clarify that thought.
>> Mhm. You can in most general terms have
a background awareness of how do I feel
right now.
>> Yeah. But I forgot to ask that question
because distracting things came up in my
life. >> Yeah. But so does that mean I lost the
>> Yeah. But so does that mean I lost the
touch with it? Does that mean I lost the
mindfulness or to if if that clarity
like that clarity might fade to some
extent or the other and that's
inevitable. But what matters is when the
clarity is lost and you kind of double
down on the actions that result from the
lack of perspective then even if you try
to regain it
>> like that's that's the difference. So if
I don't say something comes up you know
people's lives are busy say you had a
clarity about the the sense field and
the peripheral the the pressure that's
there underneath it and so on
>> something comes up factual requirement
to deal with things that preoccupies
your attention so you lose that clarity
but then you're saying now but if I
don't double down in actions of well I
presume unsuitable kind. So say I don't
double down but I lost the clarity
because I got distracted. Does that mean
I lost the touch with it? So I haven't
acted out but I haven't regained I
haven't maintained the clarity either.
>> Yes but that's not a problem in itself
because you will see if you didn't act
out and double down. If you wanted to
reestablish the clarity it would it
wouldn't be that difficult. But if you
did double down and you did just
proliferate in further actions, you
would see that even if you try to bring
up these ideas, the whole thing is now
abstract because you're just
kind of inflamed, so to speak, from all
this indulgent indulgence that you
engage with. So that neutral kind of
forgetfulness will not um
will not um
it's it it doesn't kind of
undo completely the degree of clarity that
completely the degree of clarity that
you could have built. You could you
could restore it just by trying to bring
it back.
>> Mhm. Mhm. So
So that's how you could measure am I
acting out too much? Am I am I kind of
um spilling out too much? It's if if
afterwards you feel like all this stuff
is just before it was clear and now it
feels kind of just abstract and and just
almost as if you hadn't clarify these
things before and you have to keep
restarting it from scratch every single
time. And you say go back to that and
you say that's because um
>> a person would have been um acted out
>> spilling out too much
>> spilling out in unsuitable ways.
>> Yeah. Even if they don't appear to them
as unsuitable ways if if it got to the
point where you can't just resume your
clarity. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> Then and and again you have it feels
like you had to start from scratch every
time. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> That means you were spilling out too
much. we were kind of um allowing too
much emphasis and focus on those factual
things that you have to deal with cuz
that's the thing uh initially it might
feel like it's it's either or like
either maintain this clarity or I engage
with these things but the more you
understand it the more you realize
>> but as I said sometimes you have to
engage with things
>> how do you then guarantee
that you won't spill out too much
>> well you have to be
>> is there a criteria
>> you have to be contained by the precepts
first and foremost.
>> Uh so then so if basically okay so then
>> spilling out too much would be if things
you have to deal with require you to
break precepts.
>> Yeah that would be the coarsest way of
spilling out too much.
>> So then doesn't matter what you need to
deal with if it's against the precepts
you don't deal with it.
>> Yeah.
>> If it's within the precepts
>> well if it's within the precepts um
you like that's what I was going to say.
you you you got to realize that
it doesn't take this kind of
um humongous concentrated effort to keep
perspective of these things because they
are already there in your experience
like the way you're being pressured
right now no matter what you're doing.
>> So the pressure is already there.
>> Yeah.
>> You're contained by the precepts.
And then you might, as I said,
legitimately get distracted by
something. >> But then you have those same things to
>> But then you have those same things to
come back to because they're still
there. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> The your whole actions and your your
decisions that you're making even if you
were ignoring the pressure would be
based on the pressure.
>> So it's not like it's it only exists
when you look at it.
>> So what you're saying, you can if you
don't spill out, you can ignore it only
so far.
>> Yeah.
>> Cuz it's there pressuring you.
>> Yeah. So then you you want to tune that
um connection with it, I guess you could
say, so that it doesn't require you to
like pause again things that are not
against the precepts.
>> Doesn't require you to pause completely
and kind of go through these mental
motions to then reestablish it. You want
to see regardless of what I'm doing, you
want to find you want to be able to find
it there. Because if you have space to
think and and plan and remember and do
whatever, you definitely have space for
this because all that stuff takes even
more effort. Mhm.
>> Than being aware of what's already
there.